Hello everyone,
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco. Hi
guys, my name is Katherine.
And today we're going
to be looking at another
lesson as part of our
sports series, and this time,
well, it's a debate, is it
a game or is it a sport?
Oh, it's a sport, you
have to work your mind.
Yeah, so we're looking
at chess, a very old,
very popular sport, very
difficult to play as well.
It takes a lot of practice
and believe me, it's
frustrating at the
beginning, and I'm still
kind of in the beginning
and immediate stages.
But yeah, it takes a lot
of practice, and it takes
so, well, it takes a lot
of time to familiarize
yourself with the rules.
Right. So we're going to be
learning a little bit more
about the pieces and
the rules today. Okay,
perfect. So we're not going
to preview anything.
Let's listen to the dialogue
for the first time, and then
we'll come back and talk
about this sport. Bobby, come
here. Look what I got here.
What is that? A chessboard.
Daddy is going to
teach you how to play. Cool.
Okay, each player gets 16 pieces.
You can be the white
ones, and I'll play
with the black pieces. Now in
the front, we are set up the pawns.
Those are the
least viable pieces,
and can only move
one space forward.
When you're about to capture
another piece, they can move one
space diagonally. What
about all these other pieces?
See this one looks like a tower?
It's called the rook. The one with
the tall hat is called the bishop.
See this little horsey?
This is called the knight.
It's a very important piece, so it's
best not to let your opponent capture it.
And these two? They
are husband and wife.
That's right. That's the
queen, and that's the king.
If the other player captures
your king, he will say, "Checkmate.
" And the game is
over. Doesn't this sound
fun? Nah. This sounds boring. I'm gonna
go play killer zombies on my playstation.
All right, so the kid is
obviously not very interested in
learning how to
play chess. Not at all.
You know, the arts of these
kind of slower games might
be replaced very
soon by video games.
Yeah, I guess it doesn't
really appeal to a little
nine-year-old or
10-year-old instead of playing
something like this
versus, yeah, shooting.
Yeah, exactly. But
it's a very great game.
It's very difficult, like we
mentioned. So we're going
to look at the name of
the pieces and the rules
that are related to these pieces in
language takeaway. Language takeaway.
Well, the first one you
might have heard before,
because this is a word
that is often used in
strategy in general. So
the word pawn, a pawn,
usually means something
that is not very important
that you can use to
distract an opponent.
All right, so on the chessboard,
you have eight pawns.
So these are the ones that
you have the most, but their
movement is very limited.
So they can only move
two spaces forward
on the first move, right?
Right. Or one space after
that. One space forward.
And only when it's
going to capture another
piece, can it move
diagonally? All right, so you
can't just go diagonally.
You have to go forward
until you're going to
take another person's piece
to capture it and to
go diagonally. All right.
But pawns is funny. You
can also use this word
when you're talking about other things like
he used her as a pawn in his little game.
No. So you want
to make an analogy.
You want to make a comparison
from life to these games.
You can you use the word
pawn pawn. Very good.
Now moving on to the other
pieces on the chessboard.
On the very far ends of the
board, you have the rook.
Okay, you got two of
these and they kind of
look like towers from
a castle. And it's a very,
well, they're very
important pieces and actually
my favorite pieces
because they're not very
important at the beginning
of a game, but at the end
of a game, boom, boom,
boom, you can do a lot of
damage because they can
go anywhere in straight lines.
Right. So they can go forward backwards and
to the sides as many spaces as they want.
The whole board
if they want. Yeah.
So easy, easy pieces to
forget about at the beginning
with they're very important.
And now next to the
rook, we have the
bishop because this is very
different from the rook
because the bishop can
also go anywhere, but
they can only go diagonally.
Right. So only diagonally.
They can also move
forward directions,
but diagonally, right?
Exactly. So you can go
forward and back up, but
it has to be in a diagonal
slanted line. Okay.
And now next to the
bishop, we have the knight.
Oh, the knight. So he's the
one galloping on the horse
like those old stories of
King Arthur, he used to
hear, but the knight can
go in an L shape and I've
never understood
this, but it's weird.
So it can move two spaces
forward and then one to the right
or one to the left, or it can move two
spaces to the right and then one forward.
So it's very strange, but it
always has to move three spaces
and in the shape of an L.
So I thought maybe he was
the drunken piece. He
can go forward a little bit,
then don't don't. Right.
So that's the knight.
It's actually a very, very
important piece as well.
And now the two main
pieces maybe of the chess
board, the queen and king.
So the king is kind of sad.
He can only move one
space, but the queen is
really the killer, because she
can do anything she wants.
This is interesting, right?
What do they make it like that?
The queen can move as many spaces
as she wants and any
direction. While the king
can do the same, any direction
he wants, but only one space.
I think there's some
similarity between
real life now is like the
queen can do anything
she wants and the king can
kind of do whatever he wants.
Well, maybe it has to
do with he has the fact
that he has to stay put
and represent the country
and she can move around
and move behind the scenes
and has a little bit
more mobility. Maybe.
Who knows? So, but in the
end, the most important piece
is the king, right? Once
the king is captured,
the game is over.
Exactly. So let's listen to
today's dialogue one more
time and slow it down a bit
and find out if the boy
understood any of these rules.
Bobby, come here. Look
what I got you. What is that?
A chessboard. Daddy's
gonna teach you how to play.
Cool. Okay. Each
player gets 16 pieces.
You can be the white ones
and I'll play with black pieces.
Now in the front,
you set up the pawns.
Those are the least viable pieces
and can only move one space forward.
When you're about to capture another
piece, it can move one space diagonally.
What about all
these other pieces?
See this one looks like a
tower? It's called the rook.
The one with the tall
hat is called the bishop.
See this little horsey?
This is called the knight.
It's a very important
piece, so it's best not
to let your opponent
capture it. And these two,
they are husband
and wife. That's right.
That's the queen and that's
the king. If the other player
captures your king,
he will say checkmate
and the game is over.
Doesn't this sound fun?
Nah. This sounds boring. I'm gonna
go play killer zombies on my playstation.
All right, we're back
and now why don't we
explain a couple of these
phrases that we also use
to explain the pieces,
but let's look at some
of these more in-depth
now in Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder. So Marco, one of the
first phrases that we heard was the word
was the phrase to move
diagonally or a diagonal line.
And so the pawns
can sometimes do this
and the bishop can do
this. What does it mean to
move diagonally? Okay,
so basically a diagonal line
is not a line that
goes straight up, right,
straight up to the sky,
for example, or to the side.
It goes at an angle,
so it's maybe going at
45 degrees or 30 degrees,
so that's a diagonal
movement or diagonal
line. The next phrase we have
is very strange, and this
one you might hear from
parents or children.
He says a little horsey.
A little horsey. So in many
languages, we have ways
of breaking down words
or adding to words to make
them sound cuter. And
this is one of those cases.
So for example, a little
puppy or a little kitty
or kitten, these are
words to make, to make
things sound cuter. So in this
case, horse becomes horsey.
So I want to ride the horsey.
It's a cute way of saying I
want to ride the cute horse.
Mommy, mommy, I
want to ride the horsey.
Exactly. So baby talk
often involves having
these rhyming words,
mommy, horsey, doggy, puppy,
a doggy, exactly, very
good. So it's a cute way
of saying something. And
now when we were talking
about the chess pieces,
when another piece
takes or gets a piece,
you say it captures it.
Okay, we say capture
because maybe it's a bit
nicer than killing it, but
what sure means taking
and keeping for
yourself. So we have a very
popular game in America
called Capture the Flag.
Right, where you have to take each other's
flag. You're stealing. You're stealing.
So yeah, this is the
term that is used in chess
to capture another
piece. Sometimes like, for
example, in Spanish, we
actually say to eat the other piece.
Really? Yeah, you
eat it. That's weird.
Well, we're a little bit more tame. Those
English-speaking countries, but to capture
is a very important
phrase. And you're going
to hear that in the news
as well, because you
can capture a person.
You can capture a criminal.
All right. And the final
word and the way that
you end a game of
chess, you say, checkmate.
Checkmate, checkmate. So
the game's over, checkmate.
Well, there's two things
that can happen at the
end of the game. And well, only one thing
can happen at the very end of the game.
But you're going to hear
these two phrases. One is check,
and the other is checkmate. So check means
that I can take your king if I want to.
Move. Right. It's in
danger. It's in danger.
But checkmate is the end
all. This means this is the very,
very last part of a game where you cannot
do anything I've trapped you, and I win.
Right. Very good. So the game is
over when somebody says checkmate.
Why don't we listen
to this dialogue
for the last time? And then
we'll come back and talk
a little bit more about
this very interesting game.
Bobby, come here.
Look what I got here.
What is that? A chessboard.
Daddy's going to teach you how
to play. Cool. Okay.
Each player gets 16 pieces.
You can be the white ones,
and I'll play with black pieces.
Now in the front, we
are set up the pawns.
Those are the
least viable pieces,
and can only move one space forward.
When you're about to capture another piece,
they can move one
space diagonally.
What about all these other pieces?
See this one looks like a tower?
It's called the rook.
The one with the
tall hat is called the
bishop. See this little horsey?
This is called the knight.
It's a very important piece, so it's
best not to let your opponent capture it.
And these two? They
are husband and wife.
That's right. That's the
queen. And that's the king.
If the other player
captures your king,
he will say, "Checkmate."
And the game is over.
Doesn't this sound fun?
Nah. This sounds boring.
I'm going to go play killer
zombies on my playstation.
Pop quiz, Marco. All
right. The word "check"
and the word "mates."
They both have meanings in
English, but put
together. What does this
phrase come from? What
could it possibly mean?
I have no idea. Why
don't you tell us?
Because I seriously don't
know where it comes from.
Okay. Well, this is
actually very interesting.
So I looked it up and I had no idea either,
because we've always just said this.
And it doesn't really make sense.
So I looked it up on the internet.
And I discovered
that the game of chess
is actually very ancient
game. And it did not
come from England. It
did not come from France.
It actually came from
Persia. And in Persian,
there are some words
that kind of became the
English words "checkmate."
That mean the king is
captured or the king is
defeated. Mm-hmm. Right.
Okay. So that's what it means.
It doesn't mean the king is dead.
No. It doesn't
mean that he's dead.
It means that he's
been taken. Okay.
And so over time, the Persian
word went into Arabic and
Arabic became French
and English. And then now,
we say "checkmate."
Checkmate. Okay. Interesting.
This is a very interesting
word. And I'm sure
everybody that's listening has a different
translation for it in their own language.
I know, for example, that in
Spanish, we would say "hakemati.
" "hakemati." Right.
So I guess like "hake" is
something's in check, it's
in danger. And then "mati"
kind of like "kill." So
maybe it's probably not
translated properly,
because as you mentioned,
it should mean defeated
or captured, not killed.
So listeners, why don't
you let us know how you
say "checkmate" in your
language, come to our
website, EnglishPod.com.
And also tell us if you
have questions about
the things we talked about
today, or if you want
to share some stories of
your own chess victories.
Please get in touch
with us on our website. Otherwise, you can
email us at EnglishPod at Praxislanguage.
com, but until then, have a
great day. Bye, everybody. Bye.